LINEAR REGRESSION
Loss
When we think about how we can assign a slope and intercept to fit a set of points, we have to define what the best fit is.

For each data point, we calculate loss, a number that measures how bad the model’s (in this case, the line’s) prediction was. You may have seen this being referred to as error.

We can think about loss as the squared distance from the point to the line. We do the squared distance (instead of just the distance) so that points above and below the line both contribute to total loss in the same way:


In this example:

For point A, the squared distance is 9 (3²)
For point B, the squared distance is 1 (1²)
So the total loss, with this model, is 10. If we found a line that had less loss than 10, that line would be a better model for this data.

Instructions
1.
We have three points, (1, 5), (2, 1), and (3, 3). We are trying to find a line that produces lowest loss.

We have provided you the list of x-values, x, and y-values, y, for these points.

Find the y-values that the line with weights m1 and b1 would predict for the x-values given. Store these in a list called y_predicted1.

2.
Find the y values that the line with weights m2 and b2 would predict for the x-values given. Store these in a list called y_predicted2.

3.
Create a variable called total_loss1 and set it equal to zero.

Then, find the sum of the squared distance between the actual y-values of the points and the y_predicted1 values by looping through the list:

Calculating the difference between y and y_predicted1
Squaring the difference
Adding it to total_loss1
4.
Create a variable called total_loss2 and set it equal to zero.

Find the sum of the squared distance between the actual y-values of the points and the y_predicted2 values by looping through the list:

Calculating the difference between y and y_predicted2
Squaring the difference
Adding it to total_loss2
5.
Print out total_loss1 and total_loss2. Out of these two lines, which would you use to model the points?

Create a variable called better_fit and assign it to 1 if line 1 fits the data better and 2 if line 2 fits the data better.

x = [1, 2, 3]
y = [5, 1, 3]

#y = x
m1 = 1
b1 = 0

#y = 0.5x + 1
m2 = 0.5
b2 = 1

y_predicted1=[m1*i+b1 for i in x]

y_predicted2=[m2*i+b2 for i in x]
total_loss1=0

for i in range(len(y)):
  total_loss1+=(y[i]-y_predicted1[i])**2

total_loss2=0
for i in range(len(y)):
  total_loss2+=(y[i]-y_predicted2[i])**2
  
print(total_loss1)
print(total_loss2)

better_fit=2


Gradient Descent for Intercept
As we try to minimize loss, we take each parameter we are changing, and move it as long as we are decreasing loss. It’s like we are moving down a hill, and stop once we reach the bottom:


The process by which we do this is called gradient descent. We move in the direction that decreases our loss the most. Gradient refers to the slope of the curve at any point.

For example, let’s say we are trying to find the intercept for a line. We currently have a guess of 10 for the intercept. At the point of 10 on the curve, the slope is downward. Therefore, if we increase the intercept, we should be lowering the loss. So we follow the gradient downwards.


We derive these gradients using calculus. It is not crucial to understand how we arrive at the gradient equation. To find the gradient of loss as intercept changes, the formula comes out to be:

\frac{2}{N}\sum_{i=1}^{N}-(y_i-(mx_i+b)) 
N
2
​	  
i=1
∑
N
​	 −(y 
i
​	 −(mx 
i
​	 +b))
N is the number of points we have in our dataset
m is the current gradient guess
b is the current intercept guess
Basically:

we find the sum of y_value - (m*x_value + b) for all the y_values and x_values we have
and then we multiply the sum by a factor of -2/N. N is the number of points we have.
Instructions
1.
Define a function called get_gradient_at_b() that takes in a set of x values, x, a set of y values, y, a slope m, and an intercept value b.

For now, have it return b, unchanged.

2.
In the get_gradient_at_b() function, we want to go through all of the x values and all of the y values and compute (y - (m*x+b)) for each of them.

Create a variable called diff that has the sum of all of these values.

Instead of returning b from the get_gradient_at_b() function, return diff.

3.
Still in the get_gradient_at_b() function, define a variable called b_gradient and set it equal to the -2/N multiplied by diff.

Note: N is the number of points, i.e. the length of the x list or the y list.

Instead of returning diff, return b_gradient.

def get_gradient_at_b(x,y,m,b):
  diff=0
  n=len(x)
  for i in range(len(x)):
    y_val = y[i]
    x_val = x[i]
    diff += (y_val - ((m * x_val) + b))
    b_gradient= (-2/n)*diff
  return b_gradient

def get_gradient_at_m(x,y,m,b):
  diff = 0
  N = len(x)
  for i in range(len(x)):
    y_val = y[i]
    x_val = x[i]
    diff += x_val*(y_val - ((m * x_val) + b))
    m_gradient = -2/N * diff
  return m_gradient



Put it Together
Now that we know how to calculate the gradient, we want to take a “step” in that direction. However, it’s important to think about whether that step is too big or too small. We don’t want to overshoot the minimum error!

We can scale the size of the step by multiplying the gradient by a learning rate.

To find a new b value, we would say:

new_b = current_b - (learning_rate * b_gradient)
where current_b is our guess for what the b value is, b_gradient is the gradient of the loss curve at our current guess, and learning_rate is proportional to the size of the step we want to take.

In a few exercises, we’ll talk about the implications of a large or small learning rate, but for now, let’s use a fairly small value.

Instructions
1.
Define a function called step_gradient() that takes in x, y, b_current, and m_current.

This function will find the gradients at b_current and m_current, and then return new b and m values that have been moved in that direction.

For now, just return the pair (b_current, m_current).

2.
Inside step_gradient(), find the gradient at b_current and the gradient at m_current using the functions defined before (get_gradient_at_b and get_gradient_at_m).

Store these gradients in variables called b_gradient and m_gradient, and return these from the function instead of b_current and m_current.

Return them as a list.

# Define your step_gradient() function here:
def step_gradient(x, y, b_current, m_current):
    b_gradient = get_gradient_at_b(x, y, b_current, m_current)
    m_gradient = get_gradient_at_m(x, y, b_current, m_current)
    return [b_gradient, m_gradient]
3.
Let’s try to move the parameter values in the direction of the gradient at a rate of 0.01.

Create variables called b and m:

b should be b_current - (0.01 * b_gradient)
m should be m_current - (0.01 * m_gradient)
Return the pair b and m from the function.

4.
We have provided Sandra’s lemonade data once more. We have a guess for what we think the b and m might be.

Call your function to perform one step of gradient descent. Store the results in the variables b and m.

Great! We have a way to step to new b and m values! Next, we will call this function a bunch, in order to move those values towards lower and lower loss.
def step_gradient(x,y,b_current,m_current):
  b_gradient= get_gradient_at_b(x,y,b_current,m_current)
  m_gradient=get_gradient_at_m(x,y,b_current,m_current)
    
  return [b_gradient, m_gradient]

def step_gradient(x,y,b_current,m_current):
  b_gradient= get_gradient_at_b(x,y,b_current,m_current)
  m_gradient=get_gradient_at_m(x,y,b_current,m_current)
  b = b_current - (0.01 * b_gradient)  
  m = m_current - (0.01 * m_gradient)
  return (b,m)

months = [1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12]
revenue = [52, 74, 79, 95, 115, 110, 129, 126, 147, 146, 156, 184]

# current intercept guess:
b = 0
# current slope guess:
m = 0

# Call your function here to update b and m
b,m=step_gradient(months,revenue,b,m)
print(b, m)

Convergence is when the loss stops changing (or changes very slowly) when parameters are changed.

Hopefully, the algorithm will converge at the best values for the parameters m and b.
Learning Rate
We want our program to be able to iteratively learn what the best m and b values are. So for each m and b pair that we guess, we want to move them in the direction of the gradients we’ve calculated. But how far do we move in that direction?

We have to choose a learning rate, which will determine how far down the loss curve we go.

A small learning rate will take a long time to converge — you might run out of time or cycles before getting an answer. A large learning rate might skip over the best value. It might never converge! Oh no!


Finding the absolute best learning rate is not necessary for training a model. You just have to find a learning rate large enough that gradient descent converges with the efficiency you need, and not so large that convergence never happens.

import codecademylib3_seaborn
import matplotlib.pyplot as plt

def get_gradient_at_b(x, y, b, m):
  N = len(x)
  diff = 0
  for i in range(N):
    x_val = x[i]
    y_val = y[i]
    diff += (y_val - ((m * x_val) + b))
  b_gradient = -(2/N) * diff  
  return b_gradient

def get_gradient_at_m(x, y, b, m):
  N = len(x)
  diff = 0
  for i in range(N):
      x_val = x[i]
      y_val = y[i]
      diff += x_val * (y_val - ((m * x_val) + b))
  m_gradient = -(2/N) * diff  
  return m_gradient

#Your step_gradient function here
def step_gradient(b_current, m_current, x, y, learning_rate):
    b_gradient = get_gradient_at_b(x, y, b_current, m_current)
    m_gradient = get_gradient_at_m(x, y, b_current, m_current)
    b = b_current - (learning_rate * b_gradient)
    m = m_current - (learning_rate * m_gradient)
    return [b, m]
  
#Your gradient_descent function here:  
def gradient_descent(x, y, learning_rate, num_iterations):
  b = 0
  m = 0
  for i in range(num_iterations):
    b, m = step_gradient(b, m, x, y, learning_rate)
  return [b,m]  

months = [1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12]
revenue = [52, 74, 79, 95, 115, 110, 129, 126, 147, 146, 156, 184]

#Uncomment the line below to run your gradient_descent function
b, m = gradient_descent(months, revenue, 0.01, 1000)

#Uncomment the lines below to see the line you've settled upon!
y = [m*x + b for x in months]

plt.plot(months, revenue, "o")
plt.plot(months, y)

plt.show()
Use Your Functions on Real Data
We have constructed a way to find the “best” b and m values using gradient descent! Let’s try this on the set of baseball players’ heights and weights that we saw at the beginning of the lesson.

Instructions
1.
Run the code in script.py.

This is a scatterplot of weight vs height.

2.
We have imported your gradient_descent() function. Call it with parameters:

X
y
num_iterations of 1000
learning_rate of 0.0001
Store the result in variables called b and m.

3.
Create a list called y_predictions. Set it to be every element of X multiplied by m and added to b.

The easiest way to do this would be a list comprehension:

new_y = [element*slope + intercept for element in y]
List comprehensions provide a concise way to create lists.

Your code should look like:

y_predictions = [m*x + b for x in X]
4.
Plot X vs y_predictions on the same plot as the scatterplot.

Does the line look right?
import codecademylib3_seaborn
from gradient_descent_funcs import gradient_descent
import pandas as pd
import matplotlib.pyplot as plt

df = pd.read_csv("heights.csv")

X = df["height"]
y = df["weight"]
b,m=gradient_descent(X,y,num_iterations=1000,learning_rate=0.0001)
y_predictions=[m*x + b for x in X]
plt.plot(X, y, 'o')
#plot your line here:
plt.plot(X, y_predictions)
plt.show()import codecademylib3_seaborn
from gradient_descent_funcs import gradient_descent
import pandas as pd
import matplotlib.pyplot as plt

df = pd.read_csv("heights.csv")

X = df["height"]
y = df["weight"]
b,m=gradient_descent(X,y,num_iterations=1000,learning_rate=0.0001)
y_predictions=[m*x + b for x in X]
plt.plot(X, y, 'o')
#plot your line here:
plt.plot(X, y_predictions)
plt.show()

Scikit-Learn
Congratulations! You’ve now built a linear regression algorithm from scratch.

Luckily, we don’t have to do this every time we want to use linear regression. We can use Python’s scikit-learn library. Scikit-learn, or sklearn, is used specifically for Machine Learning. Inside the linear_model module, there is a LinearRegression() function we can use:

from sklearn.linear_model import LinearRegression
You can first create a LinearRegression model, and then fit it to your x and y data:

line_fitter = LinearRegression()
line_fitter.fit(X, y)
The .fit() method gives the model two variables that are useful to us:

the line_fitter.coef_, which contains the slope
the line_fitter.intercept_, which contains the intercept
We can also use the .predict() function to pass in x-values and receive the y-values that this line would predict:

y_predicted = line_fitter.predict(X)
Note: the num_iterations and the learning_rate that you learned about in your own implementation have default values within scikit-learn, so you don’t need to worry about setting them specifically!

https://www.discoverdatascience.org/online/masters-in-data-science/



